Whereas writing to a file infers that we are
writing to a new file or overwriting an existing
file, the append command adds text to the end
of an existing file. We have established that,
in gaming, one or more configuration files
may be needed to store essential information,
such as a player’s statistics. For this append
example, we will use a variation of the file we
have used throughout this section. This version,
315-append, will use a file named 315-message.txt.
In the first four lines, we open the file in
write mode, write two statements to the file,
and then close the file. Let’s say that some time
has passed in the game, and we need to append some
text to the end of this text file. First, let’s
ensure any new text goes onto a new line. On line
three, I will add a backslash and n inside the
quoted text to indicate the want for a new line
after this text is added to the text file. Next,
and this is a small example of reusing code, which
is always preferable to retyping code, I will copy
the open statement from line 1 to line 6. Then,
I will change the mode from w to a for append.
As is the case with the r and w modes, a plus
sign indicates opening the file in read and write
mode. On the next line of code, line 7, I will add
a write statement to add the player name to the
text file. Then, on line 8, I will copy down the
close function to close the file. So that we can
see this code work properly, in two stages, I will
comment out the last three lines of code. We will
cover commenting in more detail elsewhere in the
course, but adding number symbols to the beginning
of a line tells Python to ignore the line. I will
run the code, and the 315-message text file is
built. In opening the file, we see the two lines
of text from lines 2 and 3 in the code. To run the
append portion of the code to mimic a real-life
situation, I will add number symbols to the
first four lines to have Python ignore that code,
and then I will uncomment lines 6 through 8 and
run that code. Then, I will open the file again,
and the append worked as text has been added
to the end of the file. Remember that regarding
existing files, write overwrites existing files
while append adds to the end of existing files.